<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno Domini M.DC.XXVI articles given in charge to be inquired upon and presented too, by the churchwardens, side- men, quest-men, and inquisitors in every parish within the province of Ardmagh [sic], in the course of the metropoliticall visitation of the same, in this present yeare begun, by the most reverend father in God, Iames, by the mercie of God, Lord Archbishop of Ardmagh, primate and metropolitane of all Ireland : the said presentments to be made upon their and every their corporall oathes, whereunto the parson, vicar, curate, and parish-clarke in every of the said parishes are to be assisting, so farre as they and every of them can, respectively in their knowledge or understanding.</title>
            <author>Church of Ireland. Province of Armagh. Archbishop (1625- 1656 : Ussher)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14265.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3422</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33149739</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33149739</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28481</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04124)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28481)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1880:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno Domini M.DC.XXVI articles given in charge to be inquired upon and presented too, by the churchwardens, side- men, quest-men, and inquisitors in every parish within the province of Ardmagh [sic], in the course of the metropoliticall visitation of the same, in this present yeare begun, by the most reverend father in God, Iames, by the mercie of God, Lord Archbishop of Ardmagh, primate and metropolitane of all Ireland : the said presentments to be made upon their and every their corporall oathes, whereunto the parson, vicar, curate, and parish-clarke in every of the said parishes are to be assisting, so farre as they and every of them can, respectively in their knowledge or understanding.</title>
                  <author>Church of Ireland. Province of Armagh. Archbishop (1625- 1656 : Ussher)</author>
                  <author>Ussher, James, 1581-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the Societie of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprinted at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Ireland --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Dublin (Ireland) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="document">
            <pb facs="tcp:28481:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>ANNO DOMINI M. DC. XXVI.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>¶ARTICLES given in charge to be inquired upon and preſented too, by the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
Side-men, Quest-men and Inquiſitors in every pariſh within the Province of Ardmagh, in the courſe of the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
viſitation of the ſame, in this preſent yeare begun, by the most Reverend Father in God, IAMES, by the mercie of God,
Lord Archbiſhop of Ardmagh, Primate and Metropolitane of all Ireland. The ſaid preſentments to be made upon their and
every their corporall Oathes; whereunto the Parſon, Vicar, Curate, and Pariſh-clarke in every of the ſaid Pariſhes, are to be
aſsiſting, ſo farre as they and every of them can, reſpectively in their knowledge or underſtanding.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>INprimis,</hi> whether is your Parſon, Vicar or Curate reſident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
in, at, and upon his Benefice, doing his duetie in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
diſtinctly the divine Service, preaching the word, and duly
adminiſtring the holy Sacraments, according to the Booke of
Common prayer?</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doth your Parſon or Vicar (being lawfully
abſent from his Cure at any time) leaue in his place a ſufficient and
conformable Curat, to celebrate divine Service, adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments,
and teach and preach the Scriptures?</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat a common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorter
to Tavernes or Alchouſes, giving himſelfe to drinking, ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
and playing at Cards, Dice, or other unlawfull games: or is he
a Striker, dueller, dancer, or hunter; or ſo reported?</p>
            <p>4 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Parſon or Vicar, or any other of or in
your pariſh, an Vſurer, or lender of his money for unlawfull gaine,
or whether is he, or are they taken or reputed ſo to be?</p>
            <p>5 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doe the Proprietaries, Parſons, Vicars &amp; other
poſſeſſors of the Churches, Chappels and their manſions within
your pariſh, keep the chancels of their rectories &amp; vicarages, &amp; other
their houſes &amp; buildings belonging to the ſame, in due reparations?</p>
            <p>6 <hi>Item,</hi> whether hath your Parſon, Vicar or Curate received
any perſons to the holy Communion, being openly knowne to be
at debate and out of charitie with their neighbours, or defamed with
any notorious crime, and not reformed?</p>
            <p>7 <hi>Item,</hi> whether hath your Parſon, Vicar or Curate denied or
neglected to viſite the ſicke, or burie the dead, being brought to the
Church, and having thereof notice?</p>
            <p>8 <hi>Item,</hi> how many Benefices or Eccleſiaſticall promotions hath
your Parſon or Vicar, &amp; how farre diſtant are they the one from
the other? what Chappels hath he to his Cures belonging? by what
names are they called, and how and by whom are they ſerved?</p>
            <p>9 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doth your Parſon, Vicar or curate miniſter the
holy Communion any otherwiſe then onely after ſuch forme and
maner as is ſet forth in the Booke of Common prayer?</p>
            <p>10 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doth your Parſon, Vicar or Curate (being no
Preacher allowed) preſume to expound the Scriptures, in his owne
Cure, or elſewhere? or doth he procure (once in a moneth at the
leaſt) a Sermon to be preached in his Cure, by Preachers lawfully
licenſed? and upon euery Sunday, when there is no Sermon, doth
he or his Curate reade ſome one of the Homilies preſcribed?</p>
            <p>11 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doth your Miniſter every Sunday and Holy-day,
halfe an houre at leaſt, before Euening prayer, examine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
the youth of your pariſh in the Catechiſme, ſet forth by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
in the booke of Common prayer; and whether doth he call
them thereunto in courſe, and whether doe the Churchwardens of
the pariſh aſsiſt him therein?</p>
            <p>12 <hi>Item,</hi> what Schoolemaſters have you in your pariſh, that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
teach privately or publickly, and not licenſed thereunto, and by
whom be they harboured?</p>
            <p>13 <hi>Item,</hi> whether be there in your pariſh any perſons that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
or abuſe, by word or deede, the Miniſters of the Church?</p>
            <p>14 <hi>Item,</hi> whether the Service of your Church be begun and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
at due and convenient houres, and whether the ſame be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by your Parſon, Vicar or Curate according to the Booke of
Common prayer?</p>
            <p>15 <hi>Item,</hi> whether any perſon within your pariſh doe wilfully
maintaine and defend any hereſie, error, or opinion contrarie or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant
to the Scriptures and doctrine of the Church?</p>
            <p>16 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be any in your pariſh that be common
drunkards, ſwearers, or blaſphemers of the name of God?</p>
            <p>17 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be any in your pariſh who have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
adulterie, fornication or inceſt, or be common baudes or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers
of ſuch lewd and evill perſons, or that be vehemently ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
thereof, or of any of the like crimes?</p>
            <p>18 <hi>Item,</hi> who they be (if any ſuch there be in your pariſh) that
be brawlers, ſlanderers, chiders, ſcholders, make-bates, and ſowers of
diſcords betweene one perſon and another, and eſpecially betweene
man &amp; wife, parents and their children, maſters and their ſeruants?</p>
            <p>19 <hi>Item,</hi> whether be there any in your pariſh that doe uſe &amp; exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
charmes, forceries, inchantments, inuocations, circles, witch-crafts,
ſoothſayings, or any like arts invented by the divell, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
in or at the time of womens travaile?</p>
            <p>20 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Church ſufficiently repayred, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
your Pulpit and Communion. Table decently furniſhed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed;
if not, whoſe default the ſame is?</p>
            <p>21 <hi>Item,</hi> whether there be in your pariſh any that (in contempt of
their own pariſh church) do reſort to any other church or chappell?</p>
            <p>22 <hi>Item,</hi> whether any Inne-holders or Alchouſe-keepers within
your pariſh do commonly uſe to ſell meat &amp; drink within the time of
common prayer, preaching or reading of the Homilies aforeſaid?</p>
            <p>23 <hi>Item,</hi> whether any in your pariſh under gouernment of their
parents or others, have made privie contractes of Matrimonie, not
calling thereunto two or moe witneſſes, nor having the conſent of
their parents, or ſuch others under whoſe gouernment they are?</p>
            <p>24 <hi>Item,</hi> whether ſuch perſons, or other in your pariſh, have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
the banes not firſt ſolemnely asked, or at unſeaſonable houres?</p>
            <p>25 <hi>Item,</hi> whether you know in your pariſh any Executors of
dead mens goods, which doe not beſtow or have not beſtowed the
ſame, eſpecially ſuch of the ſaid goods as were bequeathed or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
to be diſtributed among the poore, repayring of highwaies,
finding of poore ſchollers, or marrying of poore maydens, or ſuch
other charitable deedes accordingly?</p>
            <p>26 <hi>Item,</hi> whether any in your pariſh do uſe to keepe abrogate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
dayes, or other then by order of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
are appointed for holy dayes by the book of Common praier?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CHANCELLORS.</head>
               <p>27 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Chancellor, Commiſsarie or Officiall
learned in the Eccleſiaſticall and civill lawes, and ſuch an one as is
xxvI. yeares old at the leaſt, &amp; hath taken ſome degree in ſchooles,
and is reaſonably well practiſed in the courſe of thoſe lawes, &amp; tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
whoſe life and converſation, no evill report hath gone?</p>
               <p>28 <hi>Item,</hi> whether your Chancellor, Commiſſarie, or any other
exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction in this Dioceſſe, their Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
actuaries, Apparitors, or ſumners have at any time wincked at,
and ſuffered adulteries, fornications, inceſts, or other like offences to
paſſe &amp; remaine unpuniſhed, or have commuted any penance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
ſpeciall licenſe of the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſſe?</p>
               <p>29 <hi>Item,</hi> what perſons are there in your pariſh that have beene
married, that have beene divorced, and have married with others,
for theſe three yeares laſt paſt? by whoſe ſentence were they divor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
and by whoſe licenſe, and by whom were they ſo married?
Declare your knowledge in the premiſſes, and what you have cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly
heard.</p>
               <p>30 <hi>Item,</hi> whether doth your Chancellor, Commiſſarie or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
for his exerciſing the Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
give any yearely rent, ſumme or ſummes of money, or other
conſideration for the ſame, to any perſon or perſons whatſoever?</p>
               <p>31 <hi>Item,</hi> is there in your pariſh any other matter or cauſe of the
cognizance of the Church above not expreſſed, worthy preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in your judgement? if any ſuch matter or cauſe there be, you
are charged likewiſe to preſent the ſame, as you are the reſt by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
of the ſame Oath.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Dublin by the Societie of Stationers. Anno 1626.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
